<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Urban Pest Management</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Urban Pest Management</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>1. Introduction</title>
      <link>/introduction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/introduction/</guid>
      <description>One definition of a pest is, any organism which causes a person discomfort or worry. Many organisms that are classified as pests in the urban environment belong to Class Insects (Insect) and Class Arachnid (spiders, ticks and mites). However many other organisms such as plants, fungi and vertebrate animals are often considered as pest species depending on the situation and the individual. In fact, one person&amp;rsquo;s pest may be another person&amp;rsquo;s pet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2. Urban Pest Management</title>
      <link>/urban-pest-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/urban-pest-management/</guid>
      <description>Urban pest management is a complex task. Technicians have to balance the client needs, wants and expectation, with the client&amp;rsquo;s ability or willingness to pay. Technicians also consider the safety of the client, the general public and the environment, the sensitivity and condition of the situation and the requirements of the control measures.
The application of more pesticide, more frequently into a difficult situation is bound to fail either in terms of pest population control or in terms of human health and safety or both.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3. Integrated Pest Management</title>
      <link>/ipm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/ipm/</guid>
      <description>Integrated Pest Management - I.P.M.
The fundamental purpose of pest management is to maintain the pest population below a level which is the concern of to the client. This population level is called the tolerance level.
The tolerance level will vary depending on the client, the pest species and the situation. For example one client may tolerate seeing a few cockroaches per day, while another will not accept any sightings. Most clients will tolerate a higher level of ant presence in their home compared to cockroach population.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5. Housekeeping Methods</title>
      <link>/housekeeping-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/housekeeping-methods/</guid>
      <description>Housekeeping applies equally to homes, shops, offices and factories. It involves the management or organisation of practices that prevent or restrict the entry, survival and/or breeding of pests.
Housekeeping methods are generally routine client activities such as cleaning, checking stock on arrival for pests, building maintenance programs, storage practices, hygiene and sanitation.
Housekeeping is an absolutely vital part of any IPM program and it will ultimately determine the degree of pest population control achieved.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6. Physical Methods</title>
      <link>/physical-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/physical-methods/</guid>
      <description>Physical methods include a wide range of options ranging from screens to traps. Physical methods are primarily focused on restricting the movement or harbourage of pests.
These methods are regularly used for the management of possums, rats and birds. However, almost every pest management situation can exploit physical control methods.
The possible physical methods of pest management are only limited by the technician&amp;rsquo;s imagination and the situation involved.
Physical methods were the most widely used techniques prior to the advent of chemical control.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7. Biological Methods</title>
      <link>/biological-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/biological-methods/</guid>
      <description>At this point of time biological control methods for use in urban pest control are quite limited. Biological methods involve the use of one biological organism to limit the population of another. The use of the Cactoblastis Moth to control prickly pear which had heavily infested vast areas of Australia, was perhaps the world&amp;rsquo;s most successful example in biological pest management.
The aim in developing biological control is to isolate a predator or parasite of a pest species which can be bred up and then released into the pest&amp;rsquo;s population.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>8. Chemical Methods</title>
      <link>/chemical-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/chemical-methods/</guid>
      <description>Chemical control methods are many and varied and have been increasingly used since the second half of the nineteenth century. Since the 1940s and 1950s, chemical control methods have tended to dominate urban pest control strategies.
The manufacturers of chemical methods have responded and continue to develop and improve products which meet the general public&amp;rsquo;s criteria for health, safety and efficiency.
Manufacturers invest many millions of dollars in the development, improvement and marketing of new products and the last thing they want to see is these products being used inappropriately by ill trained, poorly equipped technicians.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9. Pest Identification and Monitoring</title>
      <link>/pest-id/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/pest-id/</guid>
      <description>The foundation of IPM is the accurate identification of the pest and ability to assess the population of that pest in the treatment zone.
Technicians in general should be able to identify the pests they most commonly encountered to genus level and preferably to species level. A 10X (ten times) power hand lens and a copy of &amp;ldquo;Urban Pest Control in Australia&amp;rdquo; by P Hadlington and J Gerozisis, are particularly valuable tools to aid in the identification process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>10. Application Technology</title>
      <link>/application-technology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/application-technology/</guid>
      <description>Getting the Pesticide from the pack to the pest safely and economically. The basic requirement of a pest control application is that it delivers the pesticide to the sites where the active compound will destroy the target pest. This is mostly achieved by applying the spray to surfaces and/or cracks and crevices
Spray equipment is designed to atomise (break up) the liquid into a large number of small drops and effectively distribute them on the required sites.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11. Nozzle Selection and Care</title>
      <link>/nozzles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/nozzles/</guid>
      <description>Nozzle selection is greatly underrated by many technicians in the urban pest control industry.
Nozzles are highly engineered pieces of equipment. They are designed to fine tolerance to deliver a given volume of liquid, in a particular pattern, and the droplets in a particular size spectrum. The use of wire, pins or needles to clean blocked nozzles , can in an instant destroy these predetermined characteristics.
These characteristics will also change as the nozzle wears.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>12. Calibration of Application Equipment</title>
      <link>/calibration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/calibration/</guid>
      <description>The calibration of application equipment is a process to determine the amount of spray applied per time interval. For calibration to be accurate, the pressure must remain constant. Changing the pressure or application equipment, especially the nozzle, will change the rate of spray applied. Thus calibration needs to be carried out for each set of equipment at a given working pressure. A pressure gauge is an essential part of most application equipment.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13. Pesticide Formulations</title>
      <link>/pesticide-formulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/pesticide-formulation/</guid>
      <description>Insecticides are seldom available in their pure form. The technical grade material or active ingredient is formulated with other components which may increase efficiency, reduce toxicity and improve ease of handling, mixing and application.
Some of the most commonly used pesticide formulations used in urban pest control include:
OIL SOLUTION CONCENTRATES are made by dissolving technical grade material in an oil based solvent. Prior to use, the oil solution concentrate is diluted with another oil based carrier such as dieseline or kerosene by the user to achieve the correct application strength.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>14. Glossary of Terms</title>
      <link>/glossary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 15:26:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/glossary/</guid>
      <description>Absorption: Is the process by which one substance is taken into another substance. For example as water is taken up by a sponge.
Active constituent (ac) - see active ingredient.
Active ingredient (ai): That part or proportion of the pesticide which is responsible for the effect on the target pest.
Acute oral LD50: Is the dose administered by mouth (oral) required to kill 50 per cent of the animal under test.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>